Captain,
队长
you're still here?
还没回去呢
Captain, are you analyzing
队长 你在复盘和
our contest against team two?
二队的比赛吗
What's your opinion on
对于上场和他们的比赛
our last contest with them?
你怎么看
I think team two did
其实我觉得上场比赛
pretty well in the last match.
二队发挥得很好
It was really a hair's breadth between winning and losing.
胜负也在毫厘之间
Honestly, we were lucky that time.
说实话 我们很幸运
We were on the brink of losing.
差一点就在输的边缘了
They've improved significantly,
他们确实进步很大
making me see them in a new light.
让我有点刮目相看了
But unfortunately, there can only be one winner.
可惜最终赢家只有一个
They won't make it to the provincial-level contest.
他们这样也无缘省赛了
Or I am
不然
looking forward to
还真想和他们
another contest with them.
再打一场呢
Bro, I get
哥们我现在特别
how you're feeling right now.
理解你的心情
We've all experienced this. I get it.
都是过来人 我懂
What?
懂什么
Xiaoyu's good,
小鱼是挺好
but if it's bound to be that way,
但是没缘分也
you can't force it.
不能强求啊
No.
没有
It's fine.
没事
Every man has got to experience
失恋是一个成熟男人的
a couple of breakups.
必经之路
I'm just…
我只是
Don't worry.
别急
Let me introduce to you a thing.
我给你推荐一个神器
A blessing for all otaku to have girlfriends.
宅男福音 脱单必备
Just by entering
只要在上面输入你的
your personal information,
个人信息
childhood experience, and spouse standard,
童年经历 择偶标准
they'll immediately pair you up with a girl
就可以瞬间匹配出一个
of similar experience,
和你有着相同经历
interests,
相同爱好
and taste.
相同品味的女孩
It's my little secret.
一般人我不告诉他
Don't underestimate it.
你还别小看它
I've already matched with a girl
我已经匹配到了一个
and we're 95%
和我有着百分之九十五
compatible.
相似的女孩
We've been chatting on and off.
最近聊得特别好
So,
所以说呀
people need to look forward.
人还是得往前看
We didn't break up.
我没失恋
I know you too well.
我还不了解你
Stop being stubborn.
嘴硬
I lost the match
我比赛输了
and I didn't get into the provincial contest.
进不了省赛了
So…
那
Cheers!
干杯
Mmm.
嗯
I'm glad that you're all
看你们一个个状态不错
looking well.
我就放心了
I was wondering
我还想着
if you'd be dejected
你们会跟之前输
like what you were the last time
给一队那样
you lost to team one.
一蹶不振呢
Well, we were novices back then.
之前不是经验少吗
Defeats are normal on the battlefield.
赛场上受点打击也正常
In my opinion,
我觉得呀
a competition goes like this.
比赛就这样 没办法
This is a competition.
这就是比赛
It's fine.
没事
We'll try harder next year.
明年我们再接再厉
We'll try harder.
再接再厉
Or
实在不行我受累
I'll come back and coach you guys.
回来给你们当教练
You
你呀
should just stay down for another year.
再留一级也行
Come on, get eating.
吃吧吃吧 赶紧吃吧
This attic is very nice.
这个阁楼真好啊
I used to think that I'd be
之前还觉得大学
able to do many things in college.
可以做很多事情
In hindsight,
仔细想想
there's really nothing much to do.
也没什么可做的
It's fine. You can come back and visit in the future.
没事 以后再回来看看
Yes!
就是
Come back whenever you like.
想回来的时候就回来呗
When you come back, we can watch a movie.
回来 看片
If you flank a class,
挂科的时候还能
you'll have somewhere to review too.
有地方复习呢
By the way,
对了
Dandan has
之前蛋蛋
been carrying a video camera
不是总是拿个摄影机
with him all around.
拍来拍去吗
He said he wanted to record
说要给我们辩论队
some vlogs for our debate team.
拍个日常微录
I've got the clips with me.
我把素材要过来了
Do you guys want to have a look?
你们想不想看
Sure!
好啊好啊
Of course! Let's take a look.
可以啊 要看 看
He's a horrible person, seriously.
这人太坏了 真的
Have some tea.
喝口茶 喝口茶
Wake yourself up.
精神精神
Hands off!
别动手
Xiong Zishi
熊子时
Mr. Sa
小撒老师
I slipped
我就是脚底不小心
by accident.
滑了一下
I didn't do it on purpose.
我真不是故意的
Perfect!
漂亮
Do you know how
你知道那个颜料
I removed the paint?
我是怎么洗干净的吗
Well, I couldn't.
洗不干净
That's enough.
你别说啦
Hao, look!
小好姐 你看
I declare
我现在宣布
that the winner of this competition is
本次比赛第一名是
Team 235.
二三五队
And I declare that the Best Debater
我也宣布一下
goes to the fourth affirmative speaker from Team AFF.
最佳辩手是正方四辩
Ma Nan.
马楠
I'd like to thank my parents,
首先要感谢我的父母
every single one of my
还要感谢团队
team members,
里的每一个人
and of course…
当然
That's enough.
行了行了行了
Let's put this here.
咱们赶紧把这放这儿
When we win,
回头啊 等赢了真的
we'll replace it with the real one.
再把真的换下来
Exactly.
没错
Thank you everyone!
谢谢大家
Yeah!
耶
All's good.
没事
There are still opportunities
说不定有机会
we may have compete
明年我们还能
together next year.
一起打比赛
Besides, we've been caught up with debate
更何况我们这两年
for the past two years
光顾着打辩论
and we haven't been able to
也没能好好享受
enjoy the college life properly.
大学生活
Let's enjoy
下半学期
the second semester.
我们好好享受吧
Yeah.
就是
I've got so many photography exhibitions that need to get going.
我有好多摄影展没办
I just feel like we've let down
就是觉得有点辜负
our old coach.
老教练
We were so close.
咱们就一步之遥了
Let's make a video call to him.
咱们跟老教练视个频啊
You guys miss him?
都想他了
Yes.
好
Let's do this.
好啊 好啊 来啊
Let me connect this to the computer.
那我连到电脑上
Hi everyone, you're all here?
大家好 都在这儿呢
Coach!
教练 教练 教练
Everyone's here!
大家都在呢
How are you going?
最近身体怎么样
It's...alright.
身体 还行吧
Let me tell you guys…
我告诉你们
Coach, your mouth is
教练 那个
too close to the camera.
嘴离镜头太近了
Okay,
行行 行了
I need to go to the bathroom. The toilet.
我得上厕所 上卫生间
Coach! Coach!
老教练 老教练
No, no, no, coach!
别别别 教练
We can see what you're doing!
我们能看见你
Coach!
教练
Oops,
哎哟
I'm sorry.
对不起啊
Listen up.
听着
What I'm about to say is very important.
接下来的话很重要
Listen carefully,
都注意听
coach might be giving us
教练可能要跟我们
an analysis of the competition.
分析比赛
Listen up.
都听着
Firstly,
一
I feel horrible in the hospital right now.
我在医院很难过
Sa, where's the braised pork you promised?
小撒 你说的红烧肉呢
I haven't even been able to have
我现在一粒花生米
a single peanut.
都没有吃到
My wife is being so strict right now,
你师娘管我
I feel like a prisoner.
管得像犯人一样
I feel horrible right now.
我真的是非常难过
You guys should come over.
你们赶紧过来呀
Ma Nan
马楠
Our old coach is frail,
老教练这样的身体状态
yet he's making an effort to cheer us on.
还在为我们振臂高呼啊
A man in the
一个风烛残年的
twilight years of his life,
老人都能
is still full of hope.
这样充满了希望
We have no excuse
我们还有什么理由
to be lax.
可以懈怠
Yes.
对
I bet our old coach wants to tell us
老教练一定跟我们说
to never give up.
不要放弃
So long as we have a glimmer of hope,
只要有一丝希望
we'll have a future.
就有未来
It doesn't matter what
不管身边的人
other people think of us.
多么看不起我们
We must have faith in ourselves.
我们都要相信自己
Yes.
嗯
Kids,
孩子们
did you get what I just said?
听明白我的话了吗
Yes, we did!
听明白了 听明白了
Coach, we promise
教练 我们一定
that we'll try our best!
会加油的
Trust us,
你放心
we'll definitely
我们一定会给
do you proud!
你争口气的
We won't let you down.
不 不让你失望
Yes, coach,
对 教练
I swear on my life
我用我的生命保证
that I'll
我一定带着他们
refresh ourselves together.
重整旗鼓
There's no need to swear on your life.
也用不着用啥生命
On some intelligence.
用点智慧
Let's- let's cheer up?
我 我们加个油吧
Sure.
好 来
One, two, three,
一 二 三
we've got this!
加油
Hey, Zishi,
喂 子时
are you free right now?
你现在有空吗
I want to meet you somewhere
我想 叫你出来
to discuss some matters.
说点事情
AI competition?
人工智能赛
According to rules from the past competitions,
根据历年的规则
a new competition
像人工智能赛
like the AI match
这种新赛事
has no specified
是没有明确的时间
time limit.
限制的
You guys can try it.
你们可以试一试
Thanks.
谢谢你啊
But as for the details,
但是具体的事宜
you'll have to consult the host
还是要向主办方他们
of the competition.
去问一下
So you can be sure about it.
这样才能确定
Xiaoyu, Nan Bei,
小鱼 南北
I wanted to let you know
我跟你说
that we have a way for getting into the provincial contest!
我们有办法进省赛了
Found it!
找到了
I remember
我想起来
coming across
我之前好像看到过
this report.
这个报道
But afterward,
但是后来
it lost its clout.
就没有什么水花了
Recently, the school's
最近学校的
AI Research Center
人类智能研究所
has been looking to translate
要把以色列的
Israel's AI debates
人工智能辩论
into Chinese.
翻译成了中文
If they do hold a competition,
如果他们办一场比赛
according the provincial competition rules,
那按照省赛规定
for school-level debates
校级辩论社举办的
held by college debate clubs,
辩论比赛
though we might not have been
虽然我们没有
shortlisted for the challenger's round,
入选踢馆环节
so long as we win,
但是只要获胜
we'll get a point.
就能有一分
So does it mean that
那是不是我们就
we'll be able to compete?
可以接比赛了
One point exactly. It's enough.
刚好一分 足够了
But will the provincial contest committee
不过那个省赛的委员会
agree to this?
会不会同意啊
We'll never know if we don't try.
不试试怎么知道
I'll go check it out
我去打听看看
and see if the school is
然后再看看学校
able to help us contact
能不能帮咱们联系一下
the AI competition's host.
人工智能赛主办方
How is it?
怎么样 怎么样
The challenger's round
因为这个踢馆赛
was over,
已经结束了
so
所以呢
the committee were very reluctant
组委会并不是很同意
with this competition.
这场比赛
We're in an AI competition.
我们这是人工智能啊
It's not conventional competitions.
又不是传统赛事
I've done the research.
我查过资料了
AI is classified as a novel competition mode.
人工智能属于创新赛程
You can apply for special competition treatment.
可以申报特殊比赛的
If it's treated as a special competition,
如果是特殊比赛的话
we can probably find loopholes in the rules and regulations.
应该有赛制漏洞可以钻
I'm good at that. I'll do it.
这我擅长 我去
No need.
不用了
I've persuaded them,
经过我的游说
and the committee has agreed to
组委会已经同意
this competition.
了这场比赛
Great.
好了好了好了
You must have put in a lot of effort into this.
你一定花了不少力气吧
Hello?
喂 你好
We would like to apply for a
我们想申请一场
one-point AI competition,
一分积分的人工智能赛
and count that into our score for the provincial contest.
算在省大赛积分
Is that possible?
里可以吗
That's possible? Thank you.
可以啊 谢谢
Well, I'm a coach.
教练嘛
With greater power comes greater responsibility.
能力越大 责任越大
So long as we're able to return to the competition,
只要能让咱们回到赛场
it doesn't hurt to
那多付出一点
go the extra mile.
那算得了什么呢
Right?
是不是
Sa, that's awesome!
小撒 你真行
Okay, okay.
好了好了好了
Before we enter the competition,
在准备比赛之前
we have another important
我们还有一件很重要的
thing to do.
事情要做
What?
什么事
Bro,
大哥
be a little more tolerant, will you?
度量大一点好不好
I've considered the whole situation.
我都已经顾全大局了
Is that not enough?
还不够度量大
Am I not tolerant?
还不够有风度啊
Nan Bei
南北
We must thank Liu Yanze for
咱们这次能继续打比赛
helping us re-enter the competition this time.
真的要多谢那个刘彦泽
I don't think things are that simple.
我觉得事情没那么简单
Do you really think that Liu Yanze is
刘彦泽是那么好心的
that kind of nice person?
人吗
Did you forget how he
忘了之前他怎么折磨
tormented us?
我们的了吗
Right, Ma Nan?
是不是 马楠
Objectively speaking,
客观上来说
I think it was only directed at you,
我觉得他只针对你
so he never left me a bad impression.
所以我对他印象还不错
Fine.
真行
Well, exactly.
就是 本来就是
So please stop
你就不要总是
being narrow-minded
以小人之心
about all this, okay?
度君子之腹好不好
If he wasn't there to help us,
他要是不是为了帮我们
what was he doing it for then?
他图这干啥
I know, Hao.
我知道了 小好姐
He wants us to return to team two
他让咱们重新回二队
so we will amass more points for them.
肯定是帮他们攒积分
So then they can continue
这样就可以重新
tormenting us.
折磨我们了
They've done with their point collection
他们 一个月前
last month.
就攒够了积分
They were the first team in our province
他们是我们省
to make it into the final.
第一个挺进决赛的队伍
I know, Ma Nan.
我知道了 马楠
What?
什么
He's into Hao.
他看上小好姐了
I'm confident in Tao Hao's
我对陶好的眼光
taste.
很自信的
I think your girlfriend should watch out.
倒是你女朋友得注意点
My girlfriend's got taste too.
我女朋友有眼光
It's precisely because she has taste
就是有眼光
that you'll have to watch out,
才需要注意点
right?
对吧
What are you talking about?
什么意思呀
Why are you guys here?
你们 来干嘛
We're here to thank you
学长 我们是来感谢你
for letting us know
告诉我们
about the AI competition.
人工智能的事情
You gave us another chance
让我们还有机会
to continue the competition.
能继续比赛
No need to thank me.
不用感谢我
I didn't do anything.
我也没做什么
Just treat it as a little thank
就当是之前你们
for helping team one
为一队攒积分
collect the points we needed.
一点点小小的回报吧
So,
说吧
what's your purpose?
什么目的
Aren't you scared of losing to us
这么帮我们
after helping us?
不怕哪天输我们手上
Twice.
两次了
I've won you twice.
我已经赢你两次了
I don't mind winning you another time.
不介意再多一次
Let me tell you, I…
我告诉你 我
What do you want to tell him?
你告诉人家什么
Say it.
说呀
Thanks.
谢
Senior Liu Yanze,
刘彦泽学长
thanks for telling us about it
谢谢你这次告诉我们
this time.
这个消息
I got really excited last time
我上次太兴奋了
so I left in a hurry
走得太急
and forgot to thank you.
忘记跟你说谢谢了
No problem. I'm looking forward
不用 我也很
to debating with you guys in the next match.
期待和你们比赛
Well,
那
we'll leave now. Thanks again!
我们先走了 再次感谢
See you at the provincial contest!
省大赛见
Um,
那个
please thank Yin Nan
麻烦也帮我跟殷楠说
for me.
一声谢谢吧
I will.
会的
No need to thank me.
不用感谢我
Just treat it like a little thank
你们权当是你们二队
for helping team one
为我们一队攒积分
collect the points
做的一些贡献的
we needed.
一些回报吧
You'll just have to kneel down
你们只需要跪下
and thank me, the great Liu Yanze,
向我刘彦泽大人
for my
感谢一下
great kindness.
大恩大德就好了
Immature.
幼稚
He's just jealous that Liu Yanze
他就是嫉妒刘彦泽
helped us deal with the problem.
帮我们解决了危机
I'm jealous? You're funny.
我嫉妒 笑了
And really, we haven't properly dealt with
而且咱们还没有
the problem
解决问题呢
or the crisis as well.
也没有解决危机
We'll still need the help
必须得由我
of me to guide us to victory.
来带领大家走向胜利
Our crisis will only be resolved
拿下下一场比赛
after winning our next competition.
才算是解决危机
Indeed, you are not jealous.
确实不是嫉妒
You see?
你看看
From the psychological perspective,
从心理学上来讲呢
only when you see someone
当你视对方为
as your competitor,
竞争对手的时候
will you be jealous of them.
才会有嫉妒心理
If you think that your opposition
但如果你觉得对
is nowhere near you
方实力远不如你
in terms of their
还没有资格
capabilities,
成为你的对手
you'll naturally not have a jealous attitude towards them.
也就不会产生嫉妒心理
Well say, Professor Ma.
看看马教授说的
And
同样的
if your opponent is much more capable than you,
如果对方强你太多
a similar rule applies.
也是这个道理
Hear that?
听到了吧
Alright,
好了好了
let's discuss
我们来商量一下
what we'll be facing
关于我们即将面临的
in the AI competition.
人工智能赛
The debate topic
我们下一场的
for our next competition
比赛的题目是
is if the development of big data reaches its acme,
大数据发展到极致
will it do more good than harm
对人类的生活是
or do more harm than good
利大于弊
on the human's life.
还是弊大于利
We are the Team AFF.
我们是正方
The AI competition rules
人工智能赛制呢
are changed ones based on the American rules.
是美式赛制的改版
There are mainly two aspects to consider.
主要是有两个方面
One, is to put forth one's argument.
一个是立论
Then, it's refutation.
然后一个是驳论
Both sides will begin with making their arguments,
先由双方开始立论
then the Team NEG will begin the refutation stage.
再由反方开始驳论
Each has a minute's time limit.
各有一分钟的时间
There are two goals in total,
主要是达到两个效果
one is a rebuttal,
一个是反驳
and another is to challenge with new questions.
再一个是提出新的问题
So basically,
所以基本上来说
it's an extended version
就是一个加长版的
of a free debate.
自由辩论呗
That's right.
没错
But
不过呀
you don't have to worry this time
你这次不用担心
about the eight second rule.
八秒的原则
Because you'll have a minute,
因为你有一分钟的时间
you can say as much as you want.
你可以敞开了说
For refuting, both sides
驳论双方呢
have ten minutes each to speak.
各有十分钟的发言时间
Taking turns.
交叉发言
But the opposite side is full of
但是对面都是
AI debaters
人工智能发言
and we don't have
咱们也没有固定
fixed roles.
上场人员
So whoever of us wants to speak
所以咱们谁想说
can just speak.
谁就上就好
Hao,
小好姐
you go break down the arguments.
你去拆下论吧
Okay.
好
I think
我觉得
the biggest problem now is
现在最大的问题是
the definition of the acme of big data.
大数据的极致是什么
Charles,
查尔斯
come here.
过来
What are you doing?
干嘛呢
I'm asking Charles to come over.
我在叫查尔斯让它过来
I don't think it know its name
它应该不知道自己
is Charles.
叫查尔斯吧
Keep your voice down, you'll make him feel bad.
你小点声 它会自卑的
Li
老李
Erya
二丫
Erdan
二蛋
Hammer
铁锤
You see?
你看
See, right?
看见了吧
Hey, senior.
学 学长
You can't stroke him backwards.
你不能这么反着摸
You need to stroke him in the same direction as his fur,
你得顺着摸
or he'll feel uncomfortable.
它会不舒服的
I don't think so. Hammer?
没有啊 铁锤
You see? He's comfortable.
你看 它多舒服
Right, Hammer?
是吧 铁锤
His name is Charles.
它叫查尔斯
It's Hammer. Hammer?
它叫铁锤 铁锤
You see?
你看
Charles, you've worked hard.
查尔斯 你辛苦了
Hammer. See?
铁锤 你看
Hey.
欸
Just once.
就一下
No, no.
不行不行 学长
Really, no. You can't.
真 真的不行 真的不行
Just a moment
就一下
Please, just for a second, okay?
拜托了 就一下好不好
You really can't.
真的不行
We have entered
已经进入到
an incomprehensible
这算理解不见的
and deep situation.
深的这个状况
What is it?
它呢 是什么呢
What are you doing?
你干嘛呢
Observing the enemy's situation.
观察敌情啊
This alpha dog really
这个阿尔法狗真的是
has no loopholes.
毫无漏洞
That was close.
太险了
Let's talk about the debate topic.
聊聊辩题呗
I'm busy.
忙着呢
What are you busy with?
你忙什么
Why are you drooping your head?
你耷拉个脑袋干嘛
Weren't you proud that you had that secret weapon
不是神器在手
to get yourself pretty ladies?
美女我有吗
At first it was.
一开始是
The two of us went to watch
我们两个去看了
what the app deemed
神器匹配出来的
was the perfect movie.
感兴趣的电影
The atmosphere was quite good.
气氛还挺不错的
I went to dinner after watching the movie.
看完电影去吃饭了
That restaurant
那个餐厅也是
was also app-recommended.
神器推荐的
But you can't just eat
但也不能光吃饭
and not chat.
不聊天吧
But when I chatted,
我这一聊天
some words might go wrong.
也不知道哪句话说错了
She got unhappy and ran away.
她就不开心地跑了
The app you used
你那个可能用的
might have been a free version.
是免费版
The experience is relatively elementary.
就是体验比较初级
You try paying for a membership.
你试试充充钱
Maybe it'll give you
可能就可以给你一个
a perfect date plan.
完美的约会攻略
That makes sense.
有道理啊
Ma Nan
马楠
You use this too?
你怎么也用这个呀
Let me tell you something.
我跟你讲
Hao is a girl you'll never meet again,
小好姐可是你下辈子
even in your next life.
都遇不到的好女孩
Keep her.
你得把握住了
Don't be half-hearted about her.
别三心二意的
Do you know why
知不知道为什么
I got the Best Debater in school
我能拿到学校最佳辩手
and you can't?
而你不能吗
That's a personal attack.
你怎么还人身攻击呢
Think about it.
你想想看
Why can Dandan
蛋蛋为什么能
match to a girl?
匹配到女孩
Big data.
大数据
If big data
如果大数据
can make him find true love…
可以让他找到真爱呢
That means that the development of big data
那就是大数据发展
has reached its acme.
到极致的优势
Not too silly.
还有的救
I'll download one, too.
我也下一个
My girlfriend is a bit tough.
我家河东狮吼
I'll leave it to you.
还是你来吧
Nickname. This Summer is a Bit...
昵称 这 这个夏天有点
That's a quick match.
这么快就有匹配吗
Hi.
你好
Sorry,
不好意思
but it's my first time using this app.
第一次用这个应用程序
What a coincidence. It's my first time, too
好巧啊 我也是第一次
Really?
真的吗
Hmm.
嗯
Let me introduce myself first.
我先自我介绍一下
I am a college student.
我是一名大学生
I'm still at school.
现在还在上学
I don't have any hobbies during my free time.
平时没什么爱好
Please take care.
希望多多关照
What about you?
请问你呢
I am a college student too.
我也是大学生
I don't have any special hobbies.
也没什么特别的爱好
Usually, I help classmates
平时也就是帮帮同学
and the teachers
帮帮老师
do some things that I'm capable of doing.
做一些力所能及的事
Occasionally, I like to take a walk
偶尔喜欢散散步
and listen to music.
听听音乐
My favorite music is
我最爱听的音乐是
Beethoven's piano repertoire.
贝多芬钢琴曲
My favorite movie is
最喜欢的电影是
"Chocolat".
《情迷朱古力》
How did you do it?
你是怎么办到的
What do you mean?
你指的是什么
You mean what I told you
是我跟你说的
regarding something in my middle school?
初中的那件事吗
No, no, no.
不不不
That thing about you.
你的那件事
I haven't seen it yet.
我还没有看到
What I'm asking is,
我问的是
how can you,
你怎么能在
in such a short time,
这么短时间内
type so many words so fast?
打出这么多字 这么快
Maybe it's because I type a lot
可能平时我学习工作
during study and work.
接触打字的比较频繁
It's probably just a matter of habit.
所以熟能生巧吧
You're an interesting girl.
你这个人很有趣啊
The same goes with you.
你也挺有意思的
Hao, what are you doing?
小好姐 你干嘛呢
You look very focused.
这么认真
I'm just looking at
我在看一些
some things related to
跟我们这次辩题有
the topics for this debate.
关的东西
Xiaoyu.
鱼
What's wrong?
你怎么了
Something happened.
出事了
Oh gosh.
我的妈呀
Why are you doing the same thing again?
你怎么老毛病又犯了
Dango, did you forget
团子 你忘记
what your dad said to you
你爸上次来
the last time he came?
怎么嘱咐你的了
No, this time it really wasn't that.
不是 这次真的不是
I was going to return it.
我本来是要退单的
But I thought about it again.
但是我一想吧
This matter is related to our
这个事跟我们这次
current resolution.
辩题有关系
So I brought it to you guys immediately.
我就赶紧拿给你们
Have a look.
看一看
I've been looking a little pale recently,
我这两天脸色不是很好
so I wanted to buy some blush.
所以我就想买个腮红
After I bought my blush,
等我买完腮红以后
the algorithm recommended
它就给我推荐了一个
a liquid foundation to me.
粉底液
After that, it was an anchor-recommended,
之后就是某主播推荐的
must-buy lipstick color.
必买口红色号
I couldn't help it
我又忍不住买了
and bought three lipsticks.
三支口红
Then something amazing happened.
神奇的事情发生了
It actually recommended a
它竟然给我推荐了一个
cosmetic storage box.
化妆品收纳盒
Then there was the mask,
之后就是面膜
mirror, comb,
镜子 梳子
until it recommended me a
直到它给我推荐了一个
dressing table
我实在买不起的
that I absolutely cannot afford.
化妆台以后
I just found out
我才发现
I was tricked.
我被套路了
This is the disadvantage
这个就是大数据
of big data's development.
发展的弊端
It's horrible.
太恐怖了
What do you mean horrible?
恐怖什么恐怖
You should return the order quickly.
你赶紧退单吧
Right, right, return the order quickly.
对对对 赶紧退单
Have something to eat.
吃点东西缓一缓
Are you hungry?
你们饿不饿
What do you want to eat?
想吃什么
I want to eat the fried leek dumplings.
我想吃韭菜盒子
Now that you say so, I want some too.
你这么一说我也想吃
Dango,
团子
order some for me.
给宝宝点个韭菜盒子吃
Okay.
好 好
What's the matter?
又怎么了
Leek dumplings.
韭菜盒子
I never buy
我从来不会买
this kind of thing.
这种东西的
The algorithm recommended it.
它自己推荐的
Are we being...
难道我们被
I'm starting to get a little bit
我 我开始有点
doubtful about our motion.
对持方产生怀疑了
I don't care.
我不管
I'm going to
我今天晚上要在
sleep in your room tonight.
你们屋睡
It's fine.
没事没事
I think big data
我觉得大数据
is really terrible.
真的太可怕了
There are drawbacks everywhere.
哪儿哪儿都是弊端
But our motion is
可是我们的持方是
that big data do more good than harm.
利大于弊呀
Whoever came up with this question has a hole in their brain.
这出题人脑子有坑
To allow AI
让大数据
manufactured using big data to argue that big data
制造的人工智能
do more harm than good
打弊大于利
And we who suffer a lot from big data
让受大数据迫害的我们
to contend that it do more good than harm.
打利大于弊
Do you think this question was
你说这题会不会
not created by human in the first place anyway?
压根就不是人出的
Are you implying…
你是说
AI knows that
人工智能知道了
its own development
自己的发展
has threatened mankind?
已经威胁到了人类
But that's not enough for it.
可它又不甘心
It doesn't know
它不知道
a legitimate reason
以什么样的理由
for it to continue developing.
继续发展
So it came up
所以它出了
with a resolution like this.
一道这样的辩题
So we can come up with reasons for it.
让我们替它想
But if the IQ of AI
可要是人工智能的智商
still requires our help to think of reasons,
还需要我们来想
then I don't see why we should feel
那也没有什么可以
threatened.
威胁了
I think AI
我觉得人工智能
is nothing to be afraid of.
没有什么可怕的
We just have to play the emotional card.
咱们只要跟它打感情牌
Take the emotional route and it will definitely lose.
走感情路线它肯定输啊
That's not necessarily true.
那可不一定
Let's try.
咱们试试呗
Okay.
好
Hao, phone.
小好姐 手机
What do you need my phone for?
你要我手机干嘛
Hey, Siri.
来 苹果语音助手
I'm here.
我在
Say something nice to me.
说句好听的我听听
I'm attracted to you,
我被你吸引
just like the earth is attracted by the sun.
如同地球被太阳吸引
I dare not get too close,
既不敢靠得太近
yet I can't escape.
又无法逃离
I'll try. Let me try.
我来 我来试试
Describe a romantic relationship in eight words.
用八个字形容感情
Hold your hand, and grow old with you.
执子之手 与子偕老
That was cheesy.
好土啊你
I'm smitten, I'm loyal, I'm genuine, I'm yours.
钟于 忠于 衷于 终于
I'm smitten with you.
钟情于你
I'm loyal to you.
忠诚于你
I'm genuine toward you.
衷心于你
I'm yours till the end.
终止于你
Wow.
哇呜
Even…
现在连
Even Siri's
连苹果语音助手
better than me at making Xiaoyu happy.
都比我会哄小鱼了
My God.
我的天爷呀
It's over. It's over.
完蛋了 完蛋了
The era when men relied on sweet talk
男人靠嘴的那个时代
is now gone forever.
已经一去不复返了
That's not a good sign.
这不是个好兆头
Don't worry.
不要急
Since everyone thinks this
既然大家都觉得这个
does more harm than good,
弊大于利
then we might as well
那我们就不如
prepare from the perspective of the other side.
从对方持方准备嘛
Wait until all the
等到这所有的
drawbacks have been found,
弊端都找到了
and the solution
那解决方法
will naturally appear.
自然就出现了嘛
Let me show you my dark cooking
给你看看我中午的
for lunch.
黑暗料理
Scrambled eggs with moon cakes and tomatoes.
月饼番茄炒蛋
Isn't it bizarrely wonderful?
是不是很奇葩
I watched a movie recently,
最近我看了一个电影
"She".
《她》
A very unconventional romance film.
一部很不寻常的爱情片
I've seen it, too. I like it a lot.
我也看过 很喜欢
The film explores
电影探讨了
the relationship between human thought
关于人类思想
and the body,
和肉体的关系
as well as the sense of belonging
和人类情感世界的
in the human emotional world.
归属感
Very good.
很不错
Although I'm not
虽然 我不
so satisfied with its ending,
太满意它的结局
it's like talking to someone once,
就像和人聊了一次
unusually but absolutely frank,
异常坦诚的天
while not knowing how to end it.
却不知道该如何结束
Hey,
哎
you've been watching Tik Tok all the morning.
你刷了一早上抖音了
Can you focus on the class?
能不能认真听讲
This is not my class.
这又不是我的课
I'm here to accompany you.
我是来陪读的
Do you know what is
你知不知道什么叫
information cocoon?
信息茧房啊
Watching Tik Tok for two hours
刷了两个小时的抖音
seems that
你以为是你
you're choosing what you want to watch,
在选择你的观看内容
but in reality,
实际上
you have been deprived
你已经被剥夺了
of the right to choose.
选择的权利
You see
它让你看什么
what it wants you to see.
你就看什么
You have been completely
你已经完完全全被
controlled by big data.
大数据控制了
You are getting more and more literate now.
你现在越来越有文化
That's because you're getting more vulgar.
那是因为你越来越俗了
This is a good point. I'll write it down.
这 这个点好 我记下来
Senior
学长
Let me make you a pot of tea.
我给你去泡壶茶吧
Puer tea or scented tea?
普洱还是花茶
No, no. It's fine.
不不不 不用
I'll just pour myself a glass of water.
我自己倒杯水就行
No, no. Sit. I'll go.
别别别 你坐着 我去
Careful, it's hot.
学长 小心烫
Thank you.
谢谢
Thanks for putting in so much time and effort
感谢你为辩论队
into this debate team.
付出了那么多
All's good, for it's part of the job.
应该的 应该的
Tao Hao,
陶好
have you been tired lately?
你最近是不是挺累的
How about
要不然
leaving the work to me?
这些工作交给我来做吧
No, senior,
学长
you can't handle it alone.
你一个人搞不定的
Let me do it.
还是我来吧
Listen to me.
你 你听我说
You go back to rest early.
你早点回去休息
You're our captain.
你是咱们的队长
Be properly prepared for the game.
好好准备比赛
Leave the rest of the jobs to me.
这些工作就交给我吧
Thank you.
谢谢学长
No problem.
没事
I'll get going, then.
那我就先走了
See you.
拜拜
Why do I feel guilty?
怎么有种负罪感
What kind of funny thing
你们俩这嘿嘿嘿的
are you two watching?
笑什么呢
Nothing.
没什么
Just looking at some pictures
就看一些猫咪
of cats and cucumbers.
和黄瓜的图片
You're still watching this?
你还看这个呢
What are you laughing at?
你笑什么呢
Dude, I met my true love.
哥们我遇到真爱了
I came across this girl on the app
我这两天划到一个妹子
who's really pretty.
长得特漂亮
The chats have been going well too.
跟我聊得也特别好
You will never believe it.
你们绝对想不到
We will meet tonight.
我们今晚就见面了
Tonight?
今晚
Yeah, just tonight.
对啊 就今晚
Meeting tonight?
今晚见面
Are you serious?
真的假的
Let me see, who is it?
我 我看看 谁呀
You can only take a look.
只能看啊
Like there is anything else I can do.
我不然还能怎么地
Stop making those noises, you colorman.
别嘬了 你个老淫魔
Sure, just take a look.
好啊 只能看一眼
What a lucky man you are, Dandan.
你艳福不浅啊 蛋蛋
Are you sure this isn't a badger game, right?
不会是仙人跳吧
That's impossible.
不可能
Through my in-depth conversations with her
通过我这几天深入
these past few days,
地交流
I realized the two of us are each other's true love.
我们俩就是真爱
We're meeting tonight.
我们今晚就要见面了
Through these couple days of conversation,
通过这几天的聊天
I find that I have a lot in common with you.
我发现和你有挺多共同点的
It feels like a friend of mine
感觉特别像我身边
who I've known for a long time.
认识了很久的朋友
Really?
是吗
I feel the same way, too.
我也有这样的感觉
It's like we really have
好像我们真的已经
known each other for a long time.
认识了很久一样
Very familiar.
特别亲切
I have a friend who is very much like you.
我有个朋友特别像你
Serious, responsible and trustworthy.
认真 负责 有责任心
She likes making
总是喜欢把
friends' issues
身边朋友的事情
on her own.
揽到自己的身上
I also have a friend like you.
我也有一个朋友像你
He's usually like
平时总是一副吊儿郎当
a lackadaisical guy.
的样子
But I know
但我知道
that he has actually taken to heart
他其实对很多事情
everything that's happening around him.
都特别地上心
He's a very good guy.
是个特别好的人
Congratulations on the match!
恭喜二位匹配度
You have reached 100%.
已达到百分之百
Would you like to connect via video-calling
是否需要视频连线
and make an appointment offline?
并线下约见
I'm sorry
不好意思啊
I have had a lot of things to deal with recently.
最近我有很多事要处理
I won't use this
不会再用这个
app ever again.
应用软件了
Sorry,
抱歉
I need to prepare for a recent,
我最近需要准备一个
and very important exam.
很重要的考试
I won't go online again.
不会再上线了
Well, I wish you all the best.
那 祝你心想事成
Take care.
保重
I also wish you all the best and take care.
也祝你诸事顺利 保重
Senior.
学长
Tao Hao.
陶好
What are you doing?
你干嘛呢
Taking a walk.
散步
I'm taking a walk, too.
我也散步呢
Why don't we walk together?
要不一起 那一起
Actually, there's also big data out there
其实大数据也有很多
that's not reliable.
不靠谱的吧
Threats don't necessarily come from
威胁不一定来自于
reliable big data.
靠谱的大数据
The unreliable side of it
它不靠谱的一面
is being exploited by human beings
被人类利用
for wars
比如说用在 战争
or for places like
或者是核电站
nuclear power plants.
之类的地方
It's dangerous.
也有危险
The debate is on big data
辩题是大数据
being developed to its acme.
发挥到极致
I think the resolution
我认为发
developing to its best
挥到极致的辩题
shouldn't have many loopholes.
应该不会有那么多漏洞
I agree.
我同意
And I have been thinking during
而且 我这两天
the past two days
一直在想啊
that if our behavior and preferences,
如果我们的行为 喜好
or even thinking,
甚至是思考
are accurately predicted
都被大数据精准
by big data,
地预测的话
what our future will actually look like.
那未来到底会怎么样
I don't think it will be that bad.
我觉得不一定会差吧
That's true.
那倒是
Higher social operation efficiency,
更高的社会运转效率
Lower personal development costs.
更低的个人发展成本
The advantage of digitization is
数据化的优势体现
efficiency.
在高效上
I'll carry on with what Nan Bei was saying.
我接南北的说啊
The core of it is
它的核心就是
whether digitization of civilization or
是如果文明或者
the world
世界被数据化
for human beings
那对我们人类来说
better or worse?
到底是更好还是更坏呢
That's not right.
不对
Before that, we must first discuss
在这之前必须先讨论
the ability of big data technology
大数据技术
to digitize
有没有将世界数据化
the world.
的能力
You know, all the known atoms of the universe
要知道现在在整个
in the whole universe,
可知宇宙的原子
added together,
数加起来
mathematically speaking,
在数学上
is hard to support
都很难以支撑这
this fantastical dream.
样的想象
Quantum mechanics can be cited everywhere.
遇事不决 量子力学
If uncertainty itself
不确定性这事本身
is one of the basic laws
如果就是宇宙的
of the universe,
基础法则之一的话
it's impossible itself.
那 这事本身就不可能
So the ultimate threat
所以最终极的威胁
is that the whole world
也就是整个世界
being completely digitized
被完全地数据化
is impossible.
是不可能的
Let's come back to real life.
那回到现实生活中
Are we able to combat
大数据的弊端
the pitfalls in big data?
咱们能不能战胜
After everyone's analysis,
经过大家的分析
I summed up the following points.
我总结了下面几个点
First,
第一
personal privacy gradually disappears
个人隐私的逐渐消失
and becomes
并且成为了
part of the commodity.
商品的一部分
Two, if data is used in an illegal way,
第二 对数据的非法使用
or it falls into the wrong hands,
或者落入不法分子手中
people will either suffer losses
会让人民蒙受损失
or lose their freedoms.
或者丧失自由
Third,
第三
the free market mechanism
自由市场机制
combined with big data technology,
结合大数据技术
will spark a rise in oligopolies,
极易出现寡头垄断
the social imbalance
以及小众需求难以满足
in resource allocation
的社会性不平衡
when niche needs are not met.
资源分配的问题
Transfer of privacy rights,
隐私权让渡
are major features
本身就是现代社会的
of the modern society.
一大特征
I even think
我甚至都觉得
this is not a singular problem.
这不是一个问题
The problem of illegal use
非法使用的问题
mainly involves
主要涉及的是
perfection of legal system construction
法制建设的完善
and prevention regulations.
和防范制度
There's a lot of progress.
现在已经进步很多了
Right.
对呀
Big data in terms of resource allocation
大数据在资源配置方面
definitely has its own problems.
确实有一定的问题
But this is precisely its strength too.
但这恰恰是它的长处
From this point of view,
从这方面来看的话
The advantages really outweigh the disadvantages.
利确实大于弊
Do you realize that
你们有没有发现
after some thorough thinking,
仔细想想
all the threats
我们所察觉到的
we perceive in fact
一切威胁
stem from
其实都来源于我们
from our own worries?
自己的担心
That's right, the fear of losing control.
没错 对失控的担心
But every step in technological advancement
但是每一次科技进步
faces risk in losing control.
都要面临失控的风险啊
Control and breakthrough itself
控制和突破
is one of the themes of
本身就是推进世界文明
promoting the world's civilization.
前进的主题之一
What remains unchanged is that
不变的是
problems associated with development should be
发展的问题就应该用
dealt with by development.
发展来解决
Right?
对吗
Exactly.
没错
Ouch.
哎哟
Umm,
那个
don't be nervous.
都别紧张啊
Treat it like a usual competition.
就跟平时比赛一样
Take it easy.
放轻松 别当回事
That is my water.
这是我的水
Why don't you take it?
要不 你 你拿着
Don't worry, Sa.
放心吧 小撒
Okay, come on.
好的 加油
Is everyone ready?
都准备好了吗
Ready.
准备好了
Let's go.
出发